<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boke of keruynge</title>
            <title>Here begynneth the boke of kervynge.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1513</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16373)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; I-4:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boke of keruynge</title>
                  <title>Here begynneth the boke of kervynge.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Enprynted by wynkyn de worde at London in fletestrete at the sygne of the sonne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The yere of our lorde god. M.CCCCC.xiij. [1513]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Here begynneth the boke of kervynge.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Table etiquette --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Courts and courtiers --  Food --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Table service --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Carving (Meat, etc.) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9387:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The boke of keruynge</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>four diners (two men -- one wearing a crown -- and two women) seated at a table, one servant standing to the left and presenting a dish; two other servants and a jester standing by in the foreground</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9387:2"/>
            <p>¶ Here begynneth the boke of keruynge and ſewyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / and all the feeſtes in the yere for the ſeruyce of a prynce or ony other eſtate as ye ſhall fy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de eche offyce the ſeruyce accordynge in this boke folowynge.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Termes of a keruer.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>BReke that dere</item>
                  <item>leſche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brawne</item>
                  <item>rere that gooſe</item>
                  <item>lyft that ſwanne</item>
                  <item>ſauce that capon</item>
                  <item>ſpoyle that henne</item>
                  <item>fruſſhe that chekyn</item>
                  <item>vnbrace that malarde</item>
                  <item>vnlace that cony</item>
                  <item>dyſmembre that heron</item>
                  <item>dyſplaye that crane</item>
                  <item>dyſfygure that pecocke</item>
                  <item>vnioynt that bytture</item>
                  <item>vntache that curlewe</item>
                  <item>alaye that feſande</item>
                  <item>wynge that partryche</item>
                  <item>wynge that quayle</item>
                  <item>mynce that plouer</item>
                  <item>thye that pegyon</item>
                  <item>border that paſty</item>
                  <item>thye that wodcocke</item>
                  <item>thye all maner of ſmall byrdes</item>
                  <item>tymbre that fyre</item>
                  <item>tyere that egge</item>
                  <item>chyne that ſamon</item>
                  <item>ſtrynge that lampraye</item>
                  <item>ſplatte that pyke</item>
                  <item>ſauce that playce</item>
                  <item>ſauce that tenche</item>
                  <item>ſplaye that breme</item>
                  <item>ſyde that haddocke</item>
                  <item>tuſke that barbell</item>
                  <item>culpon that troute</item>
                  <item>fynne that cheuen</item>
                  <item>tranſſene that ele</item>
                  <item>traunche that ſturgyon</item>
                  <item>vndertraunche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purpos</item>
                  <item>tayme that crabbe</item>
                  <item>barbe that lopſter</item>
               </list>
               <trailer>¶ Here hendeth the goodly termes.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Here begynneth Butler and Panter.</head>
               <p>THou ſhalte be Butler and Panter all the fyrſt yere / and ye muſte haue thre pantry knyues / one knyfe to ſquare tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>choure loues / an other to be a
<pb facs="tcp:9387:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>chyppere / the thyrde ſhall be ſharpe to make ſmothe tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>choures / than chyppe your ſoueraynes brede hote and all other brede let it be a daye olde / houſholde bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de thre dayes olde / trenchour brede foure dayes olde / than loke your ſalte be whyte and drye / the planer ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of Iuory two inches brode &amp; thre inches longe / &amp; loke that youre ſalte ſeller lydde touche not the ſalte / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loke your table clothes towelles and napkyns be fayre folden in a cheſte or ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vpon a perche / than loke your table knyues he fayre pullyſſhed &amp; your ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes clene / than loke ye haue two tarryours a more &amp; a leſſe &amp; wyne cannelles of boxe made accordynge / a ſharpe gymlot &amp; faucettes. And whan ye ſette a pype on broche do thus / ſet it foure fynger brede aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nether chyme vpwardes aſlaunte / and than ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyes neuer a ryſe. Alſo loke ye haue in all ſeaſons but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cheſe apples peres nottes plommes grapes dates fygges &amp; rayſyns compoſt grene gynger and charde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quynce. Serue faſtynge butter plommes dameſons cheryes and grapes. after mete peres nottes ſtrawberyes hurtelberyes &amp; harde cheſe. Alſo brandrels or pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyns with carawey in confetes. After ſouper roſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples &amp; peres with blaunche poudre &amp; harde cheſe / be ware of cowe creme &amp; of good ſtrawberyes hurtelberyes Iouncat for theſe wyll make your ſouerayne ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke but he ete harde cheſe / harde cheſe hath theſe ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / it wyll kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke open / butt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> is holſome fyrſt &amp; laſt for it wyll do awaye all poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / mylke creme &amp; Iouncat they wyll cloſe the mawe &amp; ſo dooth a poſſet / therfore ete harde cheſe &amp; drynke romney mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / beware of grene ſallettes &amp; rawe fruytes for they wyll make your ſourayne ſeke / therfore ſet not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:9387:3"/>by ſuche metes as wyll ſet your tethe on edge ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ete an almonde &amp; harde cheſe / but ete non moche cheſe without romney modon. Alſo yf dyuers dry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes yf theyr fumoſytees haue dyſpleaſed your ſouerayne let hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ete a rawe apple and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fumoſytees wyll ceaſe meſure is a mery mene &amp; it be well vſed / abſtyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is to be prayſed wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god therwith is pleaſed. Alſo take good hede of your wynes euery nyght with a candell bothe rede wyne and ſwete wyne &amp; loke they reboyle nor leke not / &amp; waſſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pype hedes euery nyght w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> colde water / &amp; loke ye haue a chynchynge yron addes and lynen clothes yf nede be / &amp; yf the reboyle ye ſhall knowe by the hyſſynge / therfore kepe an empty pype with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyes of coloured roſe &amp; drawe the reboyled wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyes &amp; it ſhal helpe it. Alſo yf your ſwete wyne pale drawe it in to a romney veſſell for leſſynge.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Here foloweth the names of wynes.</head>
                  <p>¶ Reed wyne / whyte wyne / clared wyne / oſey / capry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>polet / renyſſhe wyne / malueſey / baſtarde / tyer romney / muſcadell / clarrey / raſpys / vernage / verna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge wyne cut / pymente and ypocras.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For to make ypocras.</head>
                  <p>¶ Take gy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / peper / graynes / canell / ſynamon / ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and tornſole / than loke ye haue fyue or ſyre bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for your ypocras to renne in &amp; a perche that your renners may ren on / than muſte ye haue .vi. peautre baſyns to ſtande vnder your bagges / than loke your ſpyce be redy / &amp; your gynger well pared or it be beten
<pb facs="tcp:9387:3"/>to poudre than loke your ſtalkes of ſynamon be well coloured &amp; ſwete canell is not ſo gentyll in operacyon ſynamon is hote and drye / graynes of paradico be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and moyſte / gynger / graynes / longe peper / and ſ<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uger ben hote and moyſt / ſynamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / canell &amp; rede wyne ben hote and drye / tornſole is holſome / for reed wyne colourynge. Now knowe ye the proporcyons of your ypocras / than bete your poudres eche by themſelfe &amp; put them in bladders &amp; hange your bagges ſure that no bage touche other / but let eche baſyn touche other let the fyrſte baſyn be of a galon and eche of the other of a potell / than put in your baſyn a galo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of reed wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne put therto your poudres and ſtyre them well / than put them in to the fyrſte bagge and let it renne / than put them in to the ſeconde bagge / than take a pece in your hande and aſſaye yf it be ſtronge of gynger / and alaye it with ſynamon / and it be ſtroge or ſynamon / alaye it with ſuger / and loke ye lette it renne thrughe ſyxe renners / &amp; your ypocras ſhall be the fyner / than put your ypocras in to a cloſe veſſell and kepe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte / for it wyll ſerue for ſewes / than ſerue your ſouerayne with wafers and ypocras. Alſo loke your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſte be fayre and clene / and your ale fyue dayes olde or men drynke it / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepe your hous of offyce clene &amp; be curtoys of anſwere te eche perſone and loke ye gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no perſone noo dowled drynke / for it wyll breke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcabbe. And whan ye laye the clothe wype y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borde cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne with a cloute / than laye a cloth a couche it is called take your felawe that one ende &amp; holde you that other ende than drawe the clothe ſtraught the bought on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter edge / take the vtter parte &amp; hange it euen / than take the thyrde clothe and laye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bought on the inner
<pb facs="tcp:9387:4"/>edge / and laye eſtat with the vpper parte halfe a fote brode / than couer thy cupborde and thyn ewery with the towell of dyaper / than take thy towell about thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necke and laye that one ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towell vpon thy lef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te arme / and there on laye your ſoueraynes napkyn / and laye on thyn arme ſeuen loues of brede with thre or foure trenchour loues with the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towell in the lefte hande as the maner is / than take thy ſalte ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler in thy lefte hande and take the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towell in your ryght hande to bere in ſpones and knyues / than ſet your ſalt on the ryght ſyde where your ſouerayne ſhall ſytte and on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lefte ſyde the ſalte ſet your tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chours / than laye your knyues &amp; ſet your brede one lofe by an other / your ſpones and your napkyns fayre folden beſyde your brede / than couer your brede and trenchoures ſpones and knyues / &amp; at euery ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table ſet a ſalte ſeller with two treachour loues / and yf ye wyll wrappe youre ſoueraynes brede ſtately ye muſte ſquare and proporcyon your brede and ſe that no lofe be more than an other / and than ſhall ye make your wrapper manly / than take a towell of reynes of two yerdes and an halfe and take the towell by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des double and laye it on the table / than take the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bought a handfull in your hande and wrappe it harde and laye the ende ſo wrapped bytwene two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welles vpon that ende ſo wrapped lay your brede bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tom to botom ſyxe or ſeuen loues / than ſet your brede manerly in fourme / and whan your ſoueraynes table is thus arayed couer all other bordes with ſalte tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choures &amp; cuppes. Alſo ſo thyn ewery be arayed with baſyns &amp; ewers &amp; water hote &amp; colde / and ſe' ye haue napkyns cuppes &amp; ſpones / &amp; ſe your pottes for wyne
<pb facs="tcp:9387:4"/>and ale be made clene and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſurnape make ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſy with a clothe vnder a fayre double napry / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towelles ende nexte you / &amp; the vtter ende of the clothe on the vtter ſyde of the table &amp; holde theſe thre endes atones &amp; folde them atones that a plyte paſſe not a fote brode / than laye it euen there it ſholde lye. And after mete waſſhe with that that is at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghte ende of the table / ye muſte guyde it out and the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhall muſt conuey it / and loke on eche clothe the ryght ſyde be outwarde &amp; drawe it ſtreyght / than muſt ye reyſe the vpper parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towell &amp; laye it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony gronynge / and at euery ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towell ye muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey halfe a yerde that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſewer may make eſtate reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and let it be. And whan your ſouerayne hath waſſhen drawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſurnape euen / than bere the ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe to the myddes of the borde &amp; take it vp before your ſouerayne &amp; bere it in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ewery agayne. And whan your ſouerayne it ſet loke your towell be aboute your necke / than make your ſouerayne curteſy / than vnco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer your brede &amp; ſet it by the ſalte &amp; laye your napkyn knyfe &amp; ſpone afore hym / than knele on your knee tyll the purpayne paſſe eyght loues / &amp; loke ye ſet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table foure loues at a meſſe / and ſe that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſone haue napkyn and ſpone / &amp; wayte well to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſewer how many dyſſhes be couered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo many cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes couer ye / than ſerue ye forth the table manerly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man may ſpeke your curteſy.</p>
                  <trailer>¶ Here endeth of the Butler and Panter yoman of the ſeller and ewery.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And here foloweth ſewynge of fleſſhe.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:9387:5"/>
               <p>THe ſewer muſte ſewe &amp; from the borde conuey all maner of potages metes &amp; ſauces / &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry daye comon with the coke and vnderſtade &amp; wyte how many dyſſhes ſhall be and ſpeke with the panter and offycers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpycery for fruytes that ſhall be ete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſtynge. Than goo to the borde of ſewynge and ſe ye haue offycers redy to conuey &amp; ſeruauntes for to bere your dyſſhes. Alſo yf marſhall ſquyers and ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of armes bo there tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerue forth your ſouerayne withouten blame.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Seruyce.</head>
                  <p>¶ Fyrſte ſette ye forthe muſtarde and brawne potage bete motton ſtewed. Feſande / ſwanne / capon / pygge venyſon bake / cuſtarde / and leche lombarde. Fruyter vaunte with a ſubtylte two potages blau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and gelly. For ſtandarde venyſon roſte kydde fawne &amp; cony / buſtarde ſtorke crane pecocke with his tayle hero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſewe bytture woodcocke partryche plouer rabet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes grete byrdes larkes doucettes paynpuffe whyte leche ambre / gelly creme of almondes curlewe brewe ſnytes quayle ſparowes martynet perche i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gelly / pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typeruys quy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces bake leche dewgarde fruy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er fayge blandrelles or pepyns with carawaye in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fettes wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fers and ypocras they be agreable. Now this feeſt is done voyde ye the table.</p>
                  <trailer>¶ Here endeth the ſewynge of fleſſhe.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynneth the keruynge of fleſſhe.</head>
               <p>THe keruer muſt knowe the keruynge and the fayre ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlynge of a knyfe and how ye ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che al maner of fowle / your knyfe muſte be fayre and
<pb facs="tcp:9387:5"/>your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des muſte be clene &amp; paſſe not two fyngers &amp; a thombe vpon your knyfe. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddes of your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſet the halfe ſure vnlaſſynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge wich two fy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers &amp; a thombe keruynge of brede layenge &amp; voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of crommes with two fyngers and a thombe / loke ye haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure / ſet neuer on fyſſhe / fleſſhe / beeſt / ne ſowle more than two fyngers and a thombe / than take your lofe in your lefte hande &amp; holde your knyfe ſurely / enbrewe not the table clothe / but wype vpon your napkyn / than take your trenchouer lofe in your lefte ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and with the edge of your table knyfe take vp your trenchours as nye the poynt as ye may / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laye foure trenchours to your ſoferayne one by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and laye theron other foure trenchours or elles twayne / than take a lofe in your lyfte hande &amp; pare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lofe rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de aboute / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cut the ouer cruſte to your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerayne and cut the nether cruſte &amp; voyde the paryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge &amp; touche the lofe no more after it is ſo ſerued / than clenſe the table that the ſewer may ſerue poure ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne. Alſo ye muſte knowe the fumoſytces of fyſſhe fleſſhe and foules &amp; all maner of ſauces accordynge to theyr appetytes theſe ben the fumoſytes / ſalte ſoure teſty fatte fryed ſenewes ſkynnes hony croupes yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge feders heddes pygyons bones all maner of legges of beſtees &amp; fowles the vtter ſyde for theſe ben fumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytees laye them neuer to your ſouerayne.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Seruyce.</head>
                  <p>¶ Take your knyfe in your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and cut brawne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſſhe as it lyeth &amp; laye it on your ſoueraynes tren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chour &amp; ſe there be muſtarde. Venyſon with fourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty is good for your ſeuerayne touche not the venyſo with your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de but with your knyſe cut it .xii. draugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:9387:6"/>with the edge of your knyfe and cut it out in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourmenty / doo in the ſame wyſe with peſen &amp; bacon befe chyne and motto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / pare the befe cut the motto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; laye to your ſouerayne / beware of fumoſytees / ſalte ſenewe fatte reſty &amp; rawe. In ſyrupe feſande partry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſtokdoue &amp; chekyns / in the left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de take them by the pynyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; with the foreparte of your knyfe lyfte vp your wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / than mynce it in to the ſyrupe / beware of ſky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne rawe &amp; ſenowe. Goos tele malarde &amp; ſwan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e reyſe the legges than the wynges / laye the body in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddes or in a nother plater / the wynges in the myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; the legges after lay the brawne bytwene the leg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / &amp; the wynges in the plater. Capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or henne of gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce lyfte the legges tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wynges &amp; caſte on wyne or ale than mynce the wynge &amp; gyue your ſouerayne. Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſande partryche plouer or lapwynge reyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynges &amp; after the legges. woodcocke bytture egryt ſnyte cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lewe &amp; heronſewe vnlace them breke of the pynyons necke &amp; becke / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reyſe the legges &amp; let the fete be on ſtyll than the wynges. A crane reyſe the wynges fyrſt &amp; beware of the trumpe in his breſt. Pecoke ſtorke bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtarde &amp; ſhouyllarde vnlace them as a crane and let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fete be on ſtyll. Quayle ſparow larke martynet pegy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ſwalowe &amp; thruſſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> legges fyrſt tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynges Fawne kyde and lambe laye the kydney to your ſouerayne tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyfe vp the ſholder &amp; gyue your ſouerayne a rybbe. Venyſon roſte cut it in the dyſſhe &amp; laye it to your ſouerayne. A cony lay hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the backe cut away the ventes bytwene the hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der legges breke the canell bone than reyſe the ſydes than lay the cony on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe on eche ſyde the chyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two ſydes departed from the chy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laye the bulke chyne &amp; ſydes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſſhe
<pb facs="tcp:9387:6"/>Alſo ye muſt my<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce foure leſſes to one morcell of mete that your ſouerayne may take it in the ſauce. All bake metes that ben hote open them a boue the coffyn &amp; all that ben colde ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theym in the mydwaye. Cuſtarde cheke them inche ſquare that your ſouerayne may ete therof. Doucettes pare awaye the ſydes &amp; the bottom beware of fumoſytes. Fruyter vaunte fruyter ſay be good bett<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan> is fruyter pouche apple fruyters ben good hote / and all colde fruters touche not. Ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſey is good hote wortes or gruell of befe or of motto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is good. Gel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly mortrus creme almondes blau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che manger Iuſſell and charlet cabage and nombles of a dere ben good / &amp; all other potage beware of.</p>
                  <trailer>¶ Here endeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keruynge of fleſſſhe.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth ſauces for all maner of fowles.</head>
               <p>MVſtarde is good with brawne befe chyne ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con &amp; motton. Vergius is good to boyled che<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyns and capon / ſwanne with cawdrons / rybbes of befe with garlycke muſtarde peper vergyus gynger ſauce to la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be pygge &amp; fawne / muſtarde &amp; ſuger to fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande partryche and conye / ſauce gamelyne to hero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſewe egryt plouer &amp; crane / to brewe curlewe ſalte ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger &amp; water of tame / to buſtarde ſhouyllarde &amp; byttu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſauce gamelyne: woodcocke lapwy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge larke quayle mertynet venyſon and ſnyte with whyte ſalte / ſparo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes &amp; throſtelles with ſalte &amp; ſynamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / thus with all metes ſauce ſhall haue the operacyons.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the ſauces for all maner of fowles and metes.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9387:7"/>
               <head>¶ Here begynneth the feeſtes and ſeruyce from Eeſter vnto whytſondaye.</head>
               <p>ON Eeſter daye &amp; ſo forthe to Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tycoſt after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the table there ſhall be ſet brede tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chours and ſpones after the eſtymacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them that ſhall ſyt there and thus ye ſhall ſerue your ſouerayne laye tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chours / &amp; yf he be of a lower degre eſtate laye fyue trenchours / &amp; yf he be of lower degre foure tren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chours / &amp; of an other degre thre trenchours / than cut brede for your ſouerayne after ye knowe his condycy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons wheder it be cutte in y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myddes or pared or elles for to be cut in ſmall peces. Alſo ye muſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mete ſhall be ſerued before youre ſouerayne &amp; namely on Eeſter daye after the gouernaunce &amp; ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countree where ye were borne. Fyrſte on that daye he ſhall ſerue a calfe ſoden and bleſſyd / and than ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> egges with grene ſauce and ſet them before the moſt pryncypall eſtate / and that lorde by cauſe of his hyghe eſtate ſhall departe them all aboute hym / than ſerue potage as wortes Iowtes or browes with be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe motto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vele / &amp; capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that ben coloured with ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron and bake metes. And the ſeconde courſe Iuſſell with mamony and roſted endoured / &amp; pegyons with bake metes as tartes chewettes &amp; flawnes &amp; other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the dyſpoſycyon of the cokes. And at ſoupertyme dyuers ſauces of motto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vele in broche after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce of the ſtewarde / and than chekyns with ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>con vele roſte pegyons or lambe &amp; kydde roſte with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heed &amp; the portenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce on lambe &amp; pygges fete with vinegre &amp; percely theron &amp; a ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſye fryed &amp; other ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke metes / ye ſhall vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de this maner of ſeruyce
<pb facs="tcp:9387:7"/>dureth to Pentecoſte ſaue fyſſhe dayes. Alſo take hede how ye ſhall araye theſe thynges before your ſoueray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / fyrſt ye ſhall ſe there be grene ſauces of ſorell or of vynes that is holde a ſauce for the fyrſt courſe / and ye ſhall begyn to reyſe the capon.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the Feeſt of Eeſter tyll Pentecoſte.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And here begynneth keruyng of all maner of fowles.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Sauce that capon.</label> ¶ Take vp a capon &amp; lyfte vp the ryght legge and the ryght wynge &amp; ſo araye forth &amp; laye hym in the plater as he ſholde flee &amp; ſerue your ſouerayne &amp; knowe well that capons or chekyns ben arayed after one ſauce the chekyns ſhall be ſauced with grene ſauce or vergyus.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Lyfte that ſwanne.</label> ¶ Take and dyghte hym as a gooſe but let hym haue a largyour brawne &amp; loke ye haue chawdron.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Alaye that feſande.</label> ¶ Take a feſande and reyſe his legges &amp; his wynges as it were an henne &amp; no ſauce but onely ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ wynge that partryche.</label> ¶ Take a partryche and reyſe his legges and his wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges as a henne / &amp; ye mynce hym ſauce hym with wyn poudre of gynger &amp; ſalte / that ſet it vpon a chaufyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſſhe of coles to warme and ſerue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ wynge that quayle.</label> ¶ Take a quayle and reyſe his legges and his wynges as an henne and no ſauce but ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Dyſplaye that crane.</label> ¶ Take a crane and vnfolde his legges and cut of his wynges by the Ioyntes than take vp his wynges and his legges and ſauce hym with poudres of gynger mus<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tarde vynegre and ſalte.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9387:8"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Dyſmembre that heron.</label> ¶ Take an heron and reyſe his legges and his wynges as a crane and ſauce hym with vynegre muſtarde pou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre of gynger and ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Vnioint that bytture.</label> ¶ Take a bytture and reyſe his legges &amp; his wynges as an heron &amp; no ſauce but ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Breke that egryt.</label> ¶ Take an egryt and reyſe his legges and his wynges as an heron and no ſauce but ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Vntache that curlewe.</label> ¶ Take a curlewe and reyſe his legges and his wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as an henne and no ſauce but ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Vntache that brewe.</label> ¶ Take a brewe and reyſe his legges and his wynges in the ſame maner and no ſauce but onely ſalte &amp; ſerue your ſouerayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Vnlace that cony.</label> ¶ Take a cony and laye hym on the backe &amp; cut awaye the ventes / than reyſe the wynges and the ſydes and laye bulke chyne and the ſydes togyder ſauce vynegre and poudre of gynger.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Breke that ſarcell.</label> ¶ Take a ſarcell or a teele and reyſe his wynges &amp; his legges and no ſauce but ſalte onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Mynce that plouer.</label> ¶ Take a plouer and reyſe his legges and his wynges as an henne and no ſauce but onely ſalte.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A ſnyte.</label> ¶ Take a ſnyte and reyſe his wynges his legges and his ſholdres as a plouer and no ſauce but ſalte.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9387:8"/>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ Thye that woodcocke.</label> ¶ Take a woodcocke &amp; reyſe his legges and his wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as an henne this done dyght the brayne. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And here begynneth the feeſt from Pentecoſt vnto mydſomer</head>
               <p>IN the ſeconde courſe for the metes before ſayd ye ſhall take for your ſauces wyne ale vynegre and poudres after the mete be &amp; gynger &amp; canell from Pentecoſt to the feeſt of ſaynt Iohn baptyſt. ¶ The fyrſt courſe ſhall be befe motton ſoden with capons or roſted / &amp; yf the capons be ſoden araye hym in the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner aforeſayd. And whan he is roſted thou muſt caſte on ſalte with wyne or with ale / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the capon by the legges &amp; caſte on the ſauce &amp; breke hym out &amp; laye hym in a dyſſhe as he ſholde flee. Fyrſt ye ſhall cut the ryght legge and the ryght ſholdre &amp; bytwene the foure membres laye the brawne of the capon with the crou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe in the ende bytwene the legges as it were poſſyble for to be Ioyned agayne togyder / &amp; other bake metes after And in the ſeconde courſe potage ſhall be Iuſſell charlet or mortrus with yonge geeſe vele porke pygy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or chekyns roſted with payne puffe / truyters and other bake metes after the ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the coke. Alſo the gooſe ought to be cut membre to membre begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge at the ryght legge and ſo forth vnder the ryght wynge &amp; not vpon the Ioynte aboue / &amp; it ought for to be eten with grene garlyke or with ſorell or tender vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes or vergyus in ſomer ſeaſon after the pleaſure of your ſouerayne. Alſo ye ſhall vnderſtande that all ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of fowle that hath hole fete ſholde be reyſed vnder the wynge and not aboue.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the feeſt from Pentecoſt to mydſomer.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9387:9"/>
               <head>And here begynneth from the feeſt of ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the baptyſt vnto Myghelmaſſe.</head>
               <p>IN the fyrſt courſe potage wortes gruell &amp; four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menty with venyſon and mortrus and peſtelles of porke with grene ſauce. Roſted capon ſwanne with chawdron. In the ſeconde courſe potage after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce of the cokes with roſted motton vele porke chekyns or endoured pygyons heron ſewes fruyters or other bake metes / &amp; take hede to the feſande he ſhall be arayed in the maner of a capon / but it ſhall be done drye without ony moyſture and he ſhall be eten with ſalte and pouder of gynger. And the heronſewe ſhall be arayed in the ſame maner without ony moyſture &amp; he ſhulde be eten with ſalte and poudre. Alſo ye ſhall vnderſtande that all maner of fowles hauynge open clawes as a capon ſhall be tyred and arayed as a capon and ſuche other.</p>
               <p>¶ From the feeſt of ſaynt Myghell vnto the feeſt of Cryſtynmaſſe.</p>
               <p>IN the fyrſt courſe potage befe motton bacon or peſtelles of porke or with gooſe capon mallarde ſwanne or feſande as it is before ſayd with tartes or bake metes or chynes of porke. In the ſeconde courſe potage mortrus or conyes or ſewe / than roſte fleſſhe motton porke vele pullettes chekyns pygyons teeles wegyons mallardes partryche woodcoke plouer byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture curlewe heronſewe / venyſon rooſt grete byrdes ſnytes fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>defayres thruſſhes fruyters chewettes befe with ſauce gelopere rooſt with ſauce pegyll &amp; other ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:9387:9"/>metes as is aforeſayde. And yf ye kerue afore your lorde or your lady ony ſoden fleſſhe kerue awaye the ſky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne aboue / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kerue reſonably of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe to your lorde or laby &amp; ſpecyally for ladyes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll ſoone be angry for theyr thoughtes ben ſoone changed / and ſome lordes wyll be ſone pleaſed &amp; ſome wyll not / as they be of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The goos &amp; ſwanne may be cut as ye do other fowles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue hole fete or elles as your lorde or your lady wyll aſke it. Alſo a ſwan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dron capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or feſande ought for to be arayed as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd / but the ſkynne muſt be had awaye / &amp; whan they be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kerued before your lorde or your lady / for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the ſkynne of all maner cloue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foted fowles is vnholſome / &amp; the ſkynne of all maner hole foted fow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holſome for to be eten. Alſo wete ye well that all maner hole foted fowles that haue theyr lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon the water theyr ſkynnes ben holſome &amp; clene for by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clenes of the water / &amp; fyſſhe is theyr lyuynge. And yf that they ete ony ſtynkynge thynge it is made ſo clene with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water that all the corrupcyon is clene gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way frome it. And the ſky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henne or chekyn ben not ſo clene for the ete foule thynges in the ſtrete / &amp; therfore the ſkynnes be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſo holſome / for it is not theyr kynde to entre in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryuer to make theyr mete voyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fylth. Mallarde gooſe or ſwanne they ete vpon the londe foule mete / but a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after theyr ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de they go to the ryuer &amp; theyr they clenſe them of theyr foule ſtynke. A feſande as it is aforeſayd / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is not holſome / than take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heddes of all felde byrdes and wood byrdes as feſande pecocke partryche wood<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cocke and curlewe for they ete in theyr degrees foule thynges as wormes todes and other ſuche.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9387:10"/>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the feeſtes and the keruynge of fleſſhe</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And here begynneth the ſewynge of fyſſhe.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The fyrſt courſe.</label> TO go to ſewynge of fyſſhe muſculade mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes in ſewe of porpas or of ſamon bacon he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge w ſuger grene fyſſhe pyke lampraye ſalens por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas roſted bake gurnarde and lampraye bake.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The ſeconde courſe.</label> ¶ Gelly whyte and rede dates in confetes congre ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon dorrey brytte turbot halybut / for ſtandarde ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe troute molette cheuene ſele eles &amp; lamprayes rooſt tenche in gelly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The thyrde courſe.</label> ¶ Freſſhe ſturgyon breme perche in gelly a Ioll of ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon ſturgyon and welkes apples &amp; peres roſted with ſuger candy. Fygges of malyke &amp; rayſyns dates cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mynced gynger / wafers and ypocras they ben agreable / this feeſt is done voyde ye the table.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth ſewynge of fyſſhe.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And here foloweth keruynge of fyſſhe.</head>
               <p>THe keruer of fyſſhe muſt ſe to peſſene &amp; four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentye the tayle and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuer ye muſt loke yf there be a ſalte purpos or ſele turrentyne &amp; do after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourme of venyſon / baken herynge laye it whole vpon your ſoueraynes trenchour / whyte hery<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in a diſſhe open it by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backe pyke out the bones &amp; the rowe &amp; ſe there be muſtarde. Of ſalte fyſſhe grene fyſſhe ſalt ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon &amp; congre pare awaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkyn / ſalte fyſſhe ſtocke fyſſhe marlynge makrell and hake with butter take awaye the bones &amp; the ſkynnes. A pyke laye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe vpon his trenchour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pyke ſauce ynoughe. A ſalte
<pb facs="tcp:9387:10"/>lampraye gobone it flatte in .vii. or .viii. peces &amp; lay it to your ſouerayne. A playce put out the water / than croſſe hym with your knyfe caſt on ſalte &amp; wyne or ale Gornarde rochet breme cheuene baſe molet roche per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſole makrell &amp; whytynge haddocke and codlynge reyſe them by the backe &amp; pyke out the bones &amp; clenſe the refet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bely. Carpe breme ſole &amp; troute backe &amp; belly togyder. Samon congre ſturgyon turbot thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole thornebacke hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fyſſhe &amp; halybut cut them in the dyſſhe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> porpas aboute / tenche in his ſauce cut it / eles &amp; lamprayes rooſt pull of the ſkynne pyke out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bones put therto vyneger &amp; poudre. A crabbe breke hym a ſonder in to a dyſſhe make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhelle clene &amp; put in the ſtuffe agayne tempre it with vynegre &amp; pouder than couer it with brede and ſende it to the kytchyn to hete / than ſet it to your ſouerayne and breke the grete clawes and lay them in a diſſhe. A creues dyght hym thus departe hym a ſonder &amp; ſlytee the belly and take out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyſſhe pare away the reed ſkynne and mynce it thynne put vynegre in the dyſſhe and ſet it on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hete. A Iol of ſturgyon cut it in thynne morſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les &amp; lay it rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de aboute the dyſſhe. Freſſhe lampraye bake open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſty / than take whyte brede and cut it thynne &amp; lay it in a dyſſhe &amp; with a ſpone take out ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lentyne &amp; lay it vpon the brede with reed wyne &amp; pou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre of ſynamon / than cut a gobone of the lampraye &amp; mynce the gobone thynne and laye it in the galentyne than ſet it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fyre to hete. Freſſhe herynge with ſalte &amp; wyne / ſhrympes wel pyked flou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dres gogyons menewes &amp; muſceles eles and lamprayes ſprottes is good in ſewe / muſculade in wortes / oyſtres i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceuy oy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters in grauy menewes in porpas ſamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſeele gelly
<pb facs="tcp:9387:11"/>whyte and reed creme of almo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des dates in comfetes peres and quynces in ſyrupe with percely rotes mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trus of houndes ſyſſhe ryſe ſtandynge.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth the keruynge of fyſſhe.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And here begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth ſauces for all maner eſ fyſſhe.</head>
               <p>MVſtarde is good for ſalte herynge ſalte fyſſhe ſalte congre ſamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſparlynge ſalte ele &amp; lynge vynegre is good with ſalte porpas turrentyne ſalte / ſturgyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſalte threpole &amp; ſalte wale / lampray with ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentyne / vergyus to roche dace breme molet baſe flou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders ſole crabbe and cheuene with poudre of ſynamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thornebacke herynge houndefyſſhe haddocke whytynge &amp; codde vynegre poudre of ſynamon &amp; gynger grene ſauce is good with grene fyſſhe &amp; halybut cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell &amp; freſſhe turbot / put not your grene ſauce awaye for it is good with muſtarde.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth for all maner of fauces for fyſſhe accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to theyr appetyte.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The chaumberlayne.</head>
               <p>THe caumberlayne muſte be dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; clenly in his offyce with his heed kembed &amp; ſo to his ſouerayne that he be not recheles &amp; ſe that he haue a clene ſherte breche petycote and doublet / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bruſſhe his hoſen within &amp; without &amp; ſe his ſhone &amp; ſlyppers be made clene / &amp; at morne whan your ſouerayne wyll aryſe warme his ſherte by the fyre / &amp; ſe ye haue a fote ſhete made in this maner. Fyrſt ſet a chayre by the fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re with a cuyſſhen an other vnder his fete / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſprede a ſhete ouer the chayre and ſe there be redy a kerchefe
<pb facs="tcp:9387:11"/>and a combe / than warme his petycote his doublet and his ſtomachere / &amp; than put on his hoſen &amp; his ſhone or ſlyppers than ſtryke vp his hoſen manerly &amp; tye them vp than lace his doublet hole by hole &amp; laye the clothe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute his necke &amp; kembe his heed / than loke ye haue a baſyn &amp; an ewer with warme water and a towell and waſſhe his handes / than knele vpon your knee &amp; aſke your ſouerayne what robe he wyll were &amp; brynge hym ſuche as your ſouerayne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth &amp; put it vpon hym than doo his gyrdell aboute hym &amp; take your leue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly &amp; go to the chyrche or chapell to your ſoueraynes cloſet &amp; laye carpentes &amp; cuyſſhens &amp; lay downe his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of prayers / than drawe the curtynes and take your leue goodly &amp; go to your ſoueraynes chambre &amp; caſt all the clothes of his bedde &amp; bete the federbedde &amp; the bol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter / but loke ye waſte no feders than ſhall the blanket<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes &amp; ſe the ſhetes be fayre &amp; ſwete or elles loke ye haue clene ſhetes / than make vp his bedde manerly than lay the hed ſhetes &amp; the pyllowes / than take vp the towel &amp; the baſyn &amp; laye carpentes aboute the bedde or wyndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes &amp; cupbordes layde with carpettes and cuyſſhyns. Alſo loke there be a good fyre brennynge bryght / &amp; ſe the hous of heſement be ſwete &amp; clene &amp; the preuy borde couered with a grene clothe and a cuyſſhyn / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe there be blanked donne or cotton for your ſouerrayne / &amp; loke ye haue baſyn &amp; euer with water &amp; a towell for your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerayne / than take of his gowne &amp; brynge him a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell to kepe hym fro colde / than brynge hym to the fyre &amp; take of his ſhone &amp; his hoſen than take a fayre kercher of reynes &amp; kembe his heed &amp; put on his kercher and his bonet / than ſprede downe his bedde laye the heed ſhete and the pyllowes / &amp; whan your ſouerayne is to bedde
<pb facs="tcp:9387:12"/>drawe the curtynes / than ſe there be morter or waxe or perchoures be redy / than dryue out dogge or catte &amp; loke there be baſyn and vrynall ſet nere your ſoueray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / than take your leue manerly that your ſouerayne may take his reſt meryly.</p>
               <trailer>¶ Here endeth of the chaumberlayne.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Here foloweth of the Marſhall and the vſſher</head>
               <p>THe Marſhall and the vſſher muſte knowe all the eſtates of the chyrche and the hyghe eſtate of a kynge with the blode royall.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a Pope hath no pere.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of an Emperour is nexte.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a kynge.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a cardynall</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a kynges ſone a prynce.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of an archebyſſhop.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a duke</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a byſſhop</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a marques</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtat of an erle</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a vycount</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a baron.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of an abbot with a myter</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of the thre chefe Iuges &amp; the Mayre of London.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of an abbot without a myter</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a knyght bacheler</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a pryour dene archedeken or knyght</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9387:12"/>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of the mayſter of the rolles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of other Iuſtices &amp; barons of the cheker</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of the mayre of Calays.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a prouyncyall a doctour dyuyne</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtat of a prothonat he is aboue the popes col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour and a doctour of bothe the lawes.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of hym that hath ben mayre of London and ſeruaunt of the lawe.</item>
                  <item>¶ The eſtate of a mayſter of the chauncery and other worſhypfull prechours of pardon and clerkes that ben gradewable / &amp; all other ordres of chaſtyte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones &amp; preeſtes worſhypfull marchauntes &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylmen all this may ſyt at the ſquyers table.</item>
                  <item>¶ An archebyſſhop and a duke may not kepe the hall but eche eſtate by them ſelfe in chaumbre or in pauylyon that neyther ſe other.</item>
                  <item>¶ Byſſhoppes Marques Erles &amp; Vycou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes all theſe theſe may ſyt two at a meſſe.</item>
                  <item>¶ A baron &amp; the mayre of London &amp; thre thefe Iuges and the ſpeker of the parlyament &amp; an abbot with a myter all theſe may ſyt two or thre at a meſſe</item>
                  <item>¶ And all other eſtates may ſyt thre or foure at a meſſe</item>
                  <item>¶ Alſo the Marſhall muſte vnderſtande and knowe the blode royall for ſome lorde is of blode royall &amp; of ſmall lyuelode. And ſome knyght is wedded to a lady of royal blode ſhe ſhal kepe the eſtate that ſhe was before. And a lady of lower degree ſhall kepe the eſtate of her lordes blode / &amp; therfore the royall blode ſhall haue the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as I haue ſhewed you here before.</item>
                  <item>¶ Alſo a marſhall muſte take hede of the byrthe and nexte of the lyne of the blode royall.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9387:13"/>
                  <item>¶ Alſo he muſt take hede of the kynges offycers of the Chaunceler Stewarde Chamberlayne Treſourer and Controller.</item>
                  <item>¶ Alſo the marſhall muſt take hede vnto ſtraungers &amp; put them to worſhyp &amp; reuerence for and they haue good chere it is your ſoueraynes honour.</item>
                  <item>¶ Alſo a Marſhall muſte take hede yf the kynge ſende to your ſouerayne ony meſſage and yf he ſend a knyght receyue hym as a baron. and yf he ſende a ſquyre recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hym as a knyght / and yf he ſende you a yoman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue hym as a ſquyer / and yf he ſende you a grome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerue hym as a yoman.</item>
                  <item>¶ Alſo it is noo rebuke to a knyght to ſette a grome of the kynge at his table.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth the boke of ſeruyce &amp; keruynge and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge &amp; all maner of offyce in his kynde vnto a prynce or ony other eſtate &amp; all the feeſtes in the yere.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Enpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by wynkyn de worde at London in Flete ſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne. The yere of our lorde god. M.CCCCC.xiii.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
                  <p>wynkyn de worde</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9387:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
